Register of the Ryszard Gontarz collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Ryszard Gontarz collection
1943-2010
2009C37
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Photocopies of Polish government and communist party documents, minutes, bulletins, reports, circulated material, and printed matter, relating to political conditions and secret service activities in Poland during the communist era.
Gontarz, Ryszard, 1930-, collector
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008, with an addition in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1930 Born in Dubno
1948 Joins Polish Workers Party (P.P.R.)
1948-1949 Involved in operations against anticommunist partisans
1949 Dismissed from Security Office (U.B.)
1962 Employed in Department I of Ministry of Internal Affairs (M.S.W.)
1962-1966 Undercover agent of the Ministry of Internal Affairs
1967 Informally connected with Security Services (S.B.) in his work as journalist
1968 Active in press campaign against March revolt
Scope and Content of Collection
Photocopies of Polish government and communist party documents, minutes, bulletins, reports, circulated material, and printed matter, relating to political conditions and secret service activities in Poland during the communist era.
Documents starting from the middle of box 7 through box 13 form an addition under the series title Incremental Materials. The materials represented in the addition are composed of articles, correspondence, internal documents, newspaper clippings, photographs, writings and research materials. The increment is organized by the research topics that Ryszard Gontarz collected. Additionally, the research topics are organized by the original titles created by Gontarz: Czarna Teczka (Black Folder), Grudziń 1970 (December 1970 protests), Jedwabne (The Jedwabne massacre), Rudolf Kastner, Komandosi (The Commandos), Komitet Obrony Robotników (Workers’ Defence Committee), Kościół (Church), Lewica Patriotyczna (Leftist Patriotic Union), Marzec 1968 (Polish political crisis of March 1968), Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza (Polish United Workers’ Party), Solidarność (Solidarity), Ukraińska Powstańcz Armia (Ukrainian Insurgent Army), Wojna Domowa (Civil War), and Zbrodnie Bermanowskie (Bermanian Crimes – referring to Jakub Berman). Additionally, there is a general Research Material category of documents that the creator kept separate. Materials in this category are composed of documents and writings pertaining to emigration and repatriotization, Władysław Gomułka, PRL (Polish People’s Republic), the views of western press on Poland, as well as articles, writings, and notes of Ryszard Gontarz.
Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980.; Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; Secret service--Poland.
- American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee. Operations in Poland, 1957-1967 (File 1)
- Bieńkowski, Władysław, Polskiego Dramatu Ciąg Dalszy, 1984 (File 1)
- Control Committee on Trade with Communist Nations, 1981 (File 1)
- Czechoslovakia. Party line explanation of 1968 invasion (File 1)
- Deklaracja Ruchu Demokratycznego, includes list of Signatories, 1977 (File 1)
- Gomulka, Stanisław. Ideological testimony, 1968 (File 1)
- Gomulka, Władysław (File 1)
- Gomulka, Władysław, Correspondence, 1981 (File 1)
- Gomulka, Władysław Moje Czterenaście Lat, undated (File 1)
- Gontarz, Ryszard, Rewolta Marcowa. Narodziny, Życie i Smierć PRL, by Jerzy Brochowski, 2001 (File 1)
- Gontarz, Ryszard, Zza Kulis Historii Polski Ludowej, 1981 (File 1)
- Grabski, Tadeusz. Speeches, 1977-1978, 1982 (File 1)
- Holoubek, Gustaw. Speech in parliament, 1980 (File 1)
- Internetowy Serwis Informacyjny, 1998 (File 1)
- Jaroszewicz, Piotr. Appeal to Parliament, 1984 (File 1)
- Katyń (File 1)
  - Jerzewski, Leonard, Dzieje Sprawy Katynia, 1980 (File 1)
  - Soviet archives, 1989 (File 1)
- Komitet Obrony Robotników, undated (File 1)
- Komitet Pamięci Ofiar Stalinizmu w Polsce, 1987-1999 (File 1)
  - General, 1994-1997 (File 1)
  - Appeals, 1997-1999 (File 1)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1999 (File 1)
  - Pamięć Narodu, 1992-1993 (File 1)
  - Skonka, Leszek, Nawróceni na pluralizm czyli KORo-Solidarnościowa obłuda, 1987 (File 2)
- Konfederacja Polski Niepodległej. Trial, 1981 (File 2)
- Konwersatorium Doświadczenie i Przyszłość, 1982 (File 2)
- Kur, Stanisław, Ogłaszam alarm, kanalie stalinowskie czają się za każdym rogiem, 1980 (File 2)
- Literárni Listy, 1968 (File 2)
- Martial Law, 1981-1982 (File 2)
  - Biuro Polityczne KC PZPR, Zadania Partii w wearunkach stanu wojennego, 1982 (File 2)
  - Grabski, Tadeusz. Letter expressing disappointment about attitude of party members, 1982 (File 2)
  - Kowalski, Jan and Malinowski Andrzej, Pod wojskową dyktaturą. Między zamrożeniem a restauracją, 1982 (File 2)
- Mazurkiewicz, Ryszard, Germanizacja polskości - zaproszenie do dyskusji, 1998 (File 2)
- Mijal, Kazimierz, Główna Przyczyna Klęski Rewolucyjnego Socjalizmu, 2000 (File 2)
- Ministerstwo Przemyslu Maszynowego, Analiza Wdrożeń Licencji, 1979 (File 2)
- Ministerstwo Spraw Wewnetrznych (File 2)
  - Department II. Profilaktyczna Działalność Słuzb Bezpieczeństwa Czterech Głównych Krajów, Kapitalistycznych, 1966 (File 2)
  - Department III (File 3)
    - Anti-socialist forces, 1977-1980 (File 3)
    - Anti-Soviet acts of protest, 1981 (File 3)
    - Appeal of Polish women to wives and mothers of party apparatus, militia and security forces, 1981 (File 3)
    - Counter-revolutionary forces, 1981-1982 (File 3)
    - Departmental directives, 1975 (File 3)
    - Departmental directives, 1979 (File 3)
    - Departmental directives, 1982 (File 3)
    - Egzekutywa Komitetu Zakładowego, 1968 (File 3)
    - Events of 1980. Origins (File 3)
    - Helsinki Group, 1980 (File 3)
    - Ideological struggle. Analysis, 1977-1979 (File 3)
    - Komitet Obrony Robotników, 1980 (File 3)
    - Kraków cultural and academic circles, 1982 (File 3)
    - Martial Law, Propaganda statistics, 1982 (File 3)
    - Martial Law, Universities, 1982 (File 3)
    - Niezależne Zrzeszenie Studentów, 1981 (File 3)
    - Plan of action in case of social conflicts, 1978 (File 3)
    - Political conditions in Poland, 1976-1977 (File 3)
    - Solidarity, 1980-1982 (File 4)
      - General, 1981 (File 4)
      - Instructions, 1981-1982 (File 4)
      - Powstanie i Dzialałność NSZZ Solidarność by Feliks Bielak, 1982 (File 4)
    - Szlachcic, Franciszek. Speech to party members in Katowice, January 1981 (File 4)
    - Towarzystwo Kursów Naukowych, 1978 (File 4)
    - Underground (File 4)
      - Activities against the state, 1980 (File 4)
      - Activities against the state, 1981 - January 1982 (File 4)
      - Illegal groups list (File 4)
      - Political parties. Analysis of political programs, 1981-1982 (File 4)
    - Western policy toward Poland, 1976 (File 4)
  - Department IV. John Paul II and his mission in the East (File 4)
  - Minister, Directives on penal code, 1973 (File 4)
  - Minister, Stachura, Bogusław, Speech to Central Committee, Jan-80 (File 4)
- Moczar, Mieczysław, case of Leon Kasman, undated (File 4)
- Nowotko, Marceli, testimonies on circumstances of death (File 4)
  - Gomułka Władysław, 1977 (File 4)
  - Loga-Sowiński, Ignacy, 1980 (File 4)
  - Toruńczyk, Romana, 1973 (File 4)
- Origins of 1981 events, Geneza wydarzeń w Polsce w drugiej połowie 1980, unknown author, undated (File 4)
- Polska Lewica Patriotyczna, Bulletin, 1996 (File 4)
- Polska Lewica Patriotyczna, Declaration, 1980 (File 4)
- Polska Lewica Patriotyczna, Statute, 1997 (File 4)
- Polska Partia Socialistyczna, émigré branch, 1978 (File 4)
- Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza (File 4)
  - General (File 4)
    - Aktywizacja przeciwników socjalizmu w warunkach kryzysu spoleczno-gospodarczego w Polsce, 1981 (File 4)
    - Political assessment or ruling class, 1982 (File 4)
  - Akademia Nauk Społecznych. Centrum Studiów Polityki i Propagandy, 1986 (File 4)
  - Calendar, 15 August - 9 September 1981 (File 4)
  - Centralna Komisja Kontroli Partyjnej. Henryk Cieśluk resignation, 1981 (File 4)
  - Communist Party of the Soviet Union. Appeal to the Central Committee of the Polish United Workers Party, 1981 (File 4)
  - Congress, Ninth, 1981 (File 4)
  - First Secretary Edward Gierek, 1978-1979 (File 4)
  - International ideological conference, Berlin, 1979 (File 5)
  - Komitet Centralny (File 5)
    - Doradcy Naukowi, 1976-1980 (File 5)
      - Part I (File 5)
      - Part II (File 5)
      - Enclosures (File 5)
    - Komisja Prawa i Praworządności, August 1981 (File 5)
    - Tenth Plenum, June 1981 (File 5)
  - Komitet Fabryczny Ursus Ocena wydarzeń w 1976 roku (File 5)
  - Komitet Warszawski (File 5)
    - Konferencja Programowo-Wyborcza, 1981 (File 5)
    - Plenum, 1981, 1982 (File 5)
  - Wydział Informacji. Dokumentacja Polityczna, 1983 (File 6)
- Polskie Porozumienie Niepodległościowe. Tradycja niepodległościowa i jej wrogowie, undated (File 6)
- Polski Ruch Narodowy, 1989 (File 6)
- Postęp i Demokracja, 1990 (File 6)
- Prokuratura Generalna. Szczepanski, Maciej Indictment, 1981 (File 6)
  - General (File 6)
  - Appendix 1 (File 6)
  - Correspondence. Patyk, Eugeniusz, 1980 (File 6)
- Ruch Porozumienia Narodowego, Przedmurze, 1982 (File 6)
- Rutkowski, Adam, O Agenturze Gestapowskiej w Getcie Warszawskiej, Biuletyn Zydowskiego Instytutu Historycznego, 1956 (File 6)
- Rzeczywistość Klub Wiedzy Społeczno Politycznej, 1981-1982 (File 6)
- Samoobrona Polska, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 7)
- Słonimski Antoni, O drażliwości Żydow, 1924 (File 7)
- Student strikes press articles, 1968 (File 7)
- Szczepański, Jan, Państwo Równoległe, 1981 (File 7)
- Tudrej, Kazimierz. Indictment for armed struggle against communist authorities, 1957 (File 7)
- Wałęsa, Lech. Interview with Oriana Fallaci, 1981 (File 7)
- Wojsko Polskie (File 7)
  - Główny Zarzad Informacji. Oddział VII, Obóz Reakcji Polskiej w Latach 1939-1945, 1948 (File 7)
  - Zawsze z Narodem. Biuletyn Specjalny Krajowej Agencji Informacyjnej wydany z okazji 35-lecia Ludowego Wojska Polskiego na zlecenie Głównego Zarządu Politycznego WP, 1978 (File 7)
- Incremental Materials, 1943-2010
  Scope and Contents
  The materials represented in this section are composed of articles, correspondence, internal documents, newspaper clippings, photographs, writings and research materials. The increment is organized by the research topics that Ryszard Gontarz collected. Additionally, the research topics are organized by the original titles created by Gontarz: Czarna Teczka (Black Folder), Grudziń 1970 (December 1970 protests), Jedwabne (The Jedwabne massacre), Rudolf Kastner, Komandosi (The Commandos), Komitet Obrony Robotników (Workers’ Defence Committee), Kościół (Church), Lewica Patriotyczna (Leftist Patriotic Union), Marzec 1968 (Polish political crisis of March 1968), Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza (Polish United Workers’ Party), Solidarność (Solidarity), Ukraińska Powstańcz Armia (Ukrainian Insurgent Army), Wojna Domowa (Civil War), and Zbrodnie Bermanowskie (Bermanian Crimes – referring to Jakub Berman). Additionally, there is a general Research Material category of documents that the creator kept separate. Materials in this category are composed of documents and writings pertaining to emigration and repatriotization, Władysław Gomułka, PRL (Polish People’s Republic), the views of western press on Poland, as well as articles, writings, and notes of Ryszard Gontarz.
  - Czarna Teczka (Black Folder) file, 1956-2000
    - Articles, 1971 (Text : 7: 9)
    - Clippings, 1968-2000 (Text : 7: 10)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1999 (Text : 7: 11)
    - Jasienica, Paweł, (Leon Lech Beynar), 1995 (Text : 7: 12)
    - Milion sprawiedliwych, circa 1980 (Text : 7: 13)
    - Notes, 1968 (Text : 7: 14)
    - Odwołanie, circa 1980 (Text : 7: 15)
    - "W Obronie Leninizmu,", crica 1970 (Text : 7: 16)
    - "Wspomnienia H.S. Trumana,", 1956 (Text : 7: 17)
    - Zarys Historii PRL, 1978 (Text : 7: 18)
    - Zrzut broni w okresie okupacji, circa 1980 (Text : 7: 19)
  - Grudzień 1970 (December 1970) file, 1964-2001
    - Articles, 1970 (Text : 7: 20)
    - Clippings, 1970-2001 (Text : 7: 21)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Text : 8: 1)
    - Mieszkańcy Szczecina!, 1971 (Text : 8: 2)
    - Notes, 1970 (Text : 8: 3)
    - Photographs, 1964 (Text : 8: 4)
    - Stoczniowcy Warskiego, 1971 (Text : 8: 5)
    - Z Zebrania Otwartego POP Wydziału/Kotlarnia, Silniki/Stoczni, Który Pierwszy Rozpoczął Wydarzenia w Gdańsku, circa 1970 (Text : 8: 6)
  - Jedwabne (The Jedwabne massacre) file, 1945-2001
    - Głos Lewicy, 1998 (Text : 8: 8)
    - Notes, 1967 (Text : 8: 9)
    - Research Materials, 1994 (Text : 8: 10)
    - Clippings, 1998-2001 (Text : 8: 7)
    - "Równouprawnienie Obywatelski czy Państwo w Państwie,", circa 1970 (Text : 8: 11)
    - Żydowska Komisja Historyczna, 1945 (Text : 8: 12)
  - Rudolf Kastner file, 1960-2004
    - Clippings, circa 1980 (Text : 8: 13)
    - "Co ujawni proces Eichmana,", 1960 (Text : 8: 14)
    - "Czy Warszawa wycofała się ze swego stanowiska wobec Izraela,", circa 1990 (Text : 8: 15)
    - Faszyzm i Syjonizm: korzenie pokrewieństwa z frontu ideologicznego, 1984 (Text : 8: 16)
    - Grinwald v.s. Kastner, circa 1980 (Text : 8: 17)
    - Izrael - Marzenia i Rzeczywistość - Rozwiązanie Problemu Palestyny, circa 1980 (Text : 8: 18)
    - Izrael - Oko w Oko z Edmundem Rothschildem, 1967 (Text : 8: 19)
    - Komunikaty, 1967 (Text : 8: 20)
    - Konsolidacja Wstecznych Sił NRF, Izraela i Syjonizmu, 1968 (Text : 8: 21)
    - Notes, 1990-2004 (Text : 8: 22)
    - O przyjaźni arabsko-radzieckiej, jej znaczeniu i środkach dla jej ochrony i utrwalenia, 1967 (Text : 8: 23)
    - "Prowokatorzy przy pracy,", 1974 (Text : 8: 24)
    - Strzały w Alei Emanuela, 1968 (Text : 8: 25)
  - Komandosi (The Commandos) file, 1969-1980
    - Do użytku wewnątrzzwiązkowego, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 1)
    - Kulisy Wydarzeń Marcowych, 1969 (Text : 9: 2)
    - Kulisy Wydarzeń Marcowych w Polsce, circa 1970 (Text : 9: 3)
    - Lityński i Blumsztein Przed Sądem, circa 1970 (Text : 9: 4)
    - Notes, circa 1970 (Text : 9: 5)
  - Komitet Obrony Robotników (Workers' Defence Committee) file, 1970-1990
    - Biuletyny Informacyjne, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 6)
    - Clippings, 1981 (Text : 9: 7)
    - "Czy KSS "KOR" Będzie Mordował Swych Przeciwników?", circa 1980 (Text : 9: 8)
    - "Czy Mogę Robić te Buty?", circa 1980 (Text : 9: 9)
    - Demokratyczna Opozycja w Polsce: Wydarzenia Czerwcowe, 1979 (Text : 9: 10)
    - "Głos,", circa 1970 (Text : 9: 11)
    - Komunikaty, circa 1970 (Text : 9: 12)
    - Kuroń, Jacek, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 13)
    - Member Bio's - KOR, circa 1990 (Text : 9: 14)
    - "Niezależność,", circa 1980 (Text : 9: 15)
    - Notes, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 16)
    - "od Nowa,", 1980 (Text : 9: 17)
    - Oświadczenia, circa 1980 (Text : 9: 18)
    - Porady Dla Zakładających Zakładowe Organizacje, circa 1970 (Text : 9: 19)
    - Program polityczny i działalność Klubu Samoobrony Społecznej, 1982 (Text : 9: 20)
    - "Robotnik,", 1980 (Text : 9: 21)
    - Stenogram - Michnik A., 1980 (Text : 9: 22)
    - "Więż,", 1975 (Text : 9: 23)
    - 1863: Polska w Oczach Rosjan, crica 1970 (Text : 9: 24)
  - Kościół (Church) file, 1980-2009
    - Articles, circa 2008 (Text : 9: 25)
    - Clippings, 1980-2000 (Text : 10: 1)
    - Embargo, 1983 (Text : 10: 2)
    - Glemp, Józef, 1982-1983 (Text : 10: 3)
    - Jan Paweł II, 1983 (Text : 10: 4)
    - "Kultura,", 1982 (Text : 10: 5)
    - Monographs, 1993-2009 (Text : 10: 6)
    - Notes, circa 1980 (Text : 10: 7)
  - Lewica Patriotyczna (Leftist Patriotic Union) file, 1943-2010
    - Articles, 1943-1980 (Text : 10: 8)
    - Correspondence, 1998 (Text : 10: 9)
    - Deklaracja członkowska, 1997 (Text : 10: 10)
    - Deklaracja programowa, circa 1990 (Text : 10: 11)
    - Do wszystkich ludzi..., circa 1990 (Text : 10: 12)
    - "Głos,", 1979-1990 (Text : 10: 13)
    - "Krajobraz po Grunwaldzie,", 2010 (Text : 10: 14)
    - Kulisy Stanu Wojennego, 1987 (Text : 10: 15)
    - Lista Obecności, 1996 (Text : 10: 16)
    - Notes, 1980-1998 (Text : 11: 1)
    - Ob. Łupaszka, 1945 (Text : 11: 2)
    - Pamphlets, 1988-1997 (Text : 11: 3)
    - Photographs, circa 1948 (Text : 11: 4)
    - Porozumienie, circa 1990 (Text : 11: 5)
    - Posłanie, 1997 (Text : 11: 6)
    - Protokoły, 1996 (Text : 11: 7)
    - Research Files, 1956-2000 (Text : 11: 8)
    - Rozdział III: Członkowie ich prawa i obowiązki, circa 1990 (Text : 11: 9)
    - Statut, 1999 (Text : 11: 10)
    - Uchwała, circa 2000 (Text : 11: 11)
    - Wykaz, 1998 (Text : 11: 12)
  - Marzec 1968 (Polish political crisis of March 1968) file, 1980-1993
    - Clippings, 1980-1993 (Text : 11: 13)
    - Kulisy marcowych wydarzeń 1968 roku, circa 1990 (Text : 11: 14)
    - Notes, circa 1990 (Text : 11: 15)
    - O Robercie Satanowskim, circa 1986 (Text : 11: 16)
    - Photographs, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 17)
    - "Pokarać rękę ślepy miecz!!!", circa 1980 (Text : 11: 18)
    - Przyczynek do Wydarzeń Marcowych 1968 r., circa 1980 (Text : 11: 19)
    - Wydarzenia marcowe 1968 r. Geneza, Przebieg, Konsekwencje, circa 1990 (Text : 11: 20)
    - II Marzec 1968, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 21)
  - Polska Zjednoczona Partia Robotnicza (Polish United Workers' Party) file, 1975-2001
    - Apele, 1981 (Text : 11: 22)
    - Articles, 2001 (Text : 11: 23)
    - Blok Komentarzowy, 1982 (Text : 11: 24)
    - Conference Address, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 25)
    - Ekstremiści, 1983 (Text : 11: 26)
    - Informacja, 1982 (Text : 11: 27)
    - List Otwarty, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 28)
    - Mandat 34, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 29)
    - Nowotko - Mołojec z początków PPR: Nieznane Relacja Władysława Gomułki i Franciszka Jóżwiaka, 1981 (Text : 11: 30)
    - Propozycja składu Komitetu Centralnego PZPR i Centralnej Komisji Rewizyjnej, 1975 (Text : 11: 31)
    - Referat sprawozdawczy egzekutywy POP przy Państwowym Teatrze Ludowym w Nowej Hucie, 1977 (Text : 11: 32)
    - Sprawozdanie, 1988 (Text : 11: 33)
    - Uchwały, 1981 (Text : 11: 34)
    - Władysław Bieńkowski Polska 1980 czyli Rachunek Partyjnego Sumienia, 1981 (Text : 11: 35)
    - Wspomnieniu z działalność w Komunistycznym Związku Młodzieży Francji w Polskich Grupach Językowych, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 36)
    - Wykaz I Sekretarzy KF, KZ w bezpośredniej współpracy KC. KW., circa 1980 (Text : 11: 37)
    - Wystąpienia, 1981 (Text : 11: 38)
    - Zagadnienia Dotyczące Działalności Resortu Spraw Wewnętrznych Zamieszczone w Programie PZPR, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 39)
    - Zagadnienia i Materiały, 1982 (Text : 11: 40)
  - Reseach Materials, 1968-2007
    - Akt Oskarżenia, 1968 (Text : 11: 41)
    - Biuletyny, 1981-1982 (Text : 11: 42)
    - Emigracja i repatriacja w latach 1936-1978 /x/ w tysiącach, circa 1980 (Text : 11: 43)
    - Gomułka, Władysław, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 1)
    - Lata Trzydzieste, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 2)
    - Listy Otwarte, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 3)
    - Narodziny PRL, 1978 (Text : 12: 4)
    - Niektóre Problemy: Powstania i Rozwoju Ludowego Wojska Polskiego, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 5)
    - Notatka, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 6)
    - Oświadczenia, 1981 (Text : 12: 7)
    - Prasa Zachodnia o Polsce, 1981 (Text : 12: 8)
    - Przesilenia i Zwroty w Dziejach Polski Ludowej, 1983 (Text : 12: 9)
    - Sowiński, Ignacy Loga, 1980 (Text : 12: 10)
    - Szymański, Tadeusz, 1986 (Text : 12: 11)
    - Światowa Organizacja Syjonistyczna, 1980 (Text : 12: 12)
    - "W ćwierćwiecze Polskiego Października. Socjalistyczna odnowa - czy kontrrewolucyjny bełkot?", 1981 (Text : 12: 13)
    - W obronie prawdy i godności narodu, 2007 (Text : 12: 14)
    - Wykaz, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 15)
    - Wystąpienie, 1980 (Text : 12: 16)
  - Solidarność (Solidarity) file, 1978-1990
    - Biuletyny, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 17)
    - Clippings, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 18)
    - Czego Chce, "Solidarność Wiejska?", 1981 (Text : 12: 19)
    - Demokracja Związkowa, 1981 (Text : 12: 20)
    - Dość Odwrotu i Złudzeń Sprzeczności Antagonistyczne Rozstrzyga Walka, circa 1990 (Text : 12: 21)
    - Komunikaty, 1980 (Text : 12: 22)
    - Kryteria Doboru na Stanowiska Kierownicze Są takie same od wielu lat, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 23)
    - Ku Nowej Polsce, crica 1980 (Text : 12: 24)
    - Listy Otwarte, 1980 (Text : 12: 25)
    - Metody KSS "KOR" - Każdy Niewygodny - To Agent SB, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 26)
    - Miscellanous, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 27)
    - O Stosowaniu Przez Władze PRL Dyskryminacji w Dziedzinie Zatrudnienia Jako Metody Walki z Demokratyczną Opozycją w Polsce, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 28)
    - Oświadczenia, circa 1980 (Text : 12: 29)
    - Powstanie i Przejawy Działalności Grup Antysocjalistycznych w Polsce, 1978 (Text : 13: 1)
    - Problem Kryteriów Doboru Kandydatów na Studia Wyższe, circa 1970 (Text : 13: 2)
    - Propaganda, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 3)
    - Przyczyny Hamujące Postęp Organizacyjny w Przedsiębiorstwie, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 4)
    - Szanse Nielegalnych Wydawnictw Obywatelskich, 1981 (Text : 13: 5)
    - To Wymaga Odpowiedzi, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 6)
  - Ukraińska Powstańcz Armia (Ukrainian Insurgent Army) file, 1980-2004
    - Apele, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 7)
    - Biuletyn Instytutu Pamięci Narodowej, 2002 (Text : 13: 8)
    - Clippings, 2001 (Text : 13: 9)
    - Deklaracja programowa, circa 2000 (Text : 13: 10)
    - Informacja, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 11)
    - List prymasa Glempa do kardynała Huzara, 2004 (Text : 13: 12)
    - Listy Otwarte, 2002 (Text : 13: 13)
    - Notatka Urzędowa, 1998 (Text : 13: 14)
    - Notes, circa 1990 (Text : 13: 15)
    - W obronie prawdy i godności narodu, circa 1990 (Text : 13: 16)
    - 60 Rocznica Ludobójstwa Dokonanego przez Oun-UPA na Ludności Polskiej Kresów Wschodnich w latach 1939-1947, 2003 (Text : 13: 17)
  - Wojna Domowa (Civil War) file, 1951-2007
    - Akt Oskarżenia, 1951 (Text : 13: 18)
    - Clippings, 2001-2007 (Text : 13: 19)
    - Morderstwo 10-ciu członków Al Pardołowa, circa 1970 (Text : 13: 20)
    - Notatka, 1967 (Text : 13: 21)
    - Notes, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 22)
    - Odpis, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 23)
    - Photographs, 1970-1980 (Text : 13: 24)
    - Rezolucja, circa 1980 (Text : 13: 25)
    - Wspomnienia, 1959 (Text : 13: 26)
    - Wykaz, 1998 (Text : 13: 27)
    - Życiorys, 1964 (Text : 13: 28)
  - Zbrodnie Bermanowskie (Bermanian Crimes - referring to Jakub Berman) file, 1949-2002
    - Clippings, 1988-2002 (Text : 13: 29)
    - Lewandowski, Jerzy, 1955 (Text : 13: 30)
    - Notes, 1949 (Text : 13: 31)
    - "Powrót,", circa 1960 (Text : 13: 32)
    - Statut Komitetu Pamięci Ofiar Stalinizmu w Polsce, 1989 (Text : 13: 33)